Lois Adler-Johnson

(865) 964-0034 · lois.c.johnson@gmail.com · loisaj.com

Summary

Public health data scientist with a unique blend of engineering, statistics, and epidemiology expertise. Applies advanced quantitative analysis skills to investigate and address health inequities in North Carolina. Promoter of open-source software and part-time baker at local grain farm.

Education

University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill

Master of Public Health in Applied Epidemiology

Chapel Hill, NC

Atlanta, GA

Aug 2021 – May 2023

Georgia Institute of Technology

Bachelor of Science in Industrial & Systems Engineering

Aug 2014 - May 2018

• Concentration in Quality & Statistics

Work & Research Experience

North Carolina Institute for Public Health

Chapel Hill, NC

Data Analyst & Advisor, Community Assessment & Strategy

Jan 2023 - Present

- Building quantitative data capacity and literacy among the public health workforce at governmental health agencies, academic institutions, and community-based organizations across North Carolina
- Providing technical assistance rooted in data equity principles for all stages of the data lifecycle, including collection, transformation, analysis, visualization, and dissemination

UNC Injury Prevention Research Center

Chapel Hill, NC

Graduate Research Assistant, NC-FASTER

Apr 2022 - Dec 2022

- Coordinated multi-institution project to improve surveillance of overdose, injury, violence prevention, and mental and behavioral health using ED visit data in NC
- Probabilistically linked NC-VDRS and NC DETECT data in R to improve firearm and suicide event surveillance
- Prepared reports and presentations on data linkage methods, results, and public health implications of our work

UNC Gillings School of Global Public Health, Health Behavior Department

Chapel Hill, NC

Graduate Research Assistant, Young Adult Alcohol Misuse in Context

Jan 2022 – Dec 2022

- Transformed and analyzed cross-sectional survey and ecological momentary assessment (EMA) data in R and SAS
- Led exploratory analysis of drinking motives and the use of harm reduction strategies
- Drafted academic manuscripts on the topic of young adult engagement in alcohol consumption harm reduction strategies in various physical and social contexts

NC DPH Injury and Violence Prevention Branch

Raleigh, NC

Social Research Specialist, Epidemiology, Surveillance and Informatics Unit

Oct 2021 - Aug 2022

- Conducted literature review on ecological associations of violent death
- Conceptualized comprehensive statewide injury and violence surveillance Tableau dashboard
- Collected and transformed injury indicators from publicly available secondary data sources in R

Workday, Inc.

Chicago, IL

Functional Consultant

Jul 2018 – June 2021

- Architected complex global deployments of Workday Absence and Time Tracking for large enterprise organizations
- Facilitated implementation workshops for large international audiences in NA, LATAM, EMEA, and APAC regions
- Used product knowledge to develop, configure, and test strategic solutions that meet customers' global needs

CDC Division of HIV/AIDS Prevention

Atlanta, GA

Team Lead for Senior Capstone

Aug 2017 - May 2018

- Developed user-friendly web-based resource allocation modeling tool to facilitate data-driven HIV funding decisions
- Built robust optimization model in R and Excel with cost, efficacy, budget, population, and uncertainty parameters

The White House

Washington, D.C.

Operations Intern, Obama Administration

Aug 2016 – Dec 2016

- Improved fulfillment efficiency for miscellaneous requests across the White House campus using original process maps
- Triaged operations requests and oversaw logistics of 27 conference rooms for all White House staff and guests

Volunteer Experience

Birth Partners at UNC Medical Center

Chapel Hill, NC

Volunteer Doula Jan 2022 – Jan 2023

Provided emotional, informational, and physical support to birthing persons before, during, and after childbirth

UN Women USA Chicago

Chicago, IL

Director of Development

Mar 2020 – Aug 2021

- Spearheaded fundraising campaigns and events that raised over \$15,000, tripling the previous year's total
- Motivated 250+ individual donors to support global UN Women initiatives (e.g., ending violence against women)

Public Affairs Committee

Jan 2019 - Aug 2021

• Assembled a collaborative community of organizations in Chicago dedicated to advancing the rights of women and girls

Field MuseumGuest Relations Volunteer, Docent

Chicago, IL Feb 2019 – Jul 2021

- Provided a positive experience for visitors through greetings, exhibit recommendations, and problem resolution
- Educated visitors on Ancient Egypt, Botany, and the museum's worldwide conservation efforts through exhibit tours

Skills & Awards

Programming & Software: R, R Shiny, Quarto, Python, ArcGIS, SAS, Stata, SQL, Tableau, Excel, HTML/CSS, Canva

Awards: UNC Gillings School of Public Health Travel Award (2022), Workday Living Our Values Award (2020), National Alpha Kappa Psi Outstanding Leader Award for Unity (2018), Georgia Tech Industrial & Systems Engineering Ambassador of Year (2017), Georgia Tech Federal Jackets Fellowship (2016)

Publications & Presentations

Peer-Reviewed Published Manuscripts

Cox, M. J., **Johnson, L.**, Roudebush, M., Godbole, A., Egan, K. L. (2024). Likelihood of engagement in protective behavioral strategies by young adults across physical and social contexts: implications for adaptive interventions. *Substance Use and Misuse*. https://doi.org/10.1080/10826084.2024.2310484. [PMID: 38308201]

Roudebush, M., Godbole, A., **Johnson, L.**, Egan, K. L., & Cox, M. J. (2023). Alcohol protective behavioral strategies for young adults: a content analysis across drinking contexts and gender. *The American Journal of Drug and Alcohol Abuse*. https://doi.org/10.1080/00952990.2023.2272035. [PMID: 38011681]

Waller, A., Harmon, K. J., Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson**, **L. C.**, (2023). Emergency Department Visits Prior to Firearm Death: The NC LEADS Project. *North Carolina Medical Journal*. https://doi.org/10.18043/001c.81274. [PMID: 39302307]

Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., & Harmon, K. J. (2023). Feasibility of linking violent death decedents to prior-month emergency department visits in North Carolina, 2019-2020. *Injury Prevention*. https://doi.org/10.1136/ip-2022-044821. [PMID: 37094916]

Peer-Reviewed Presentations (Completed or Accepted for Presentation via Competitive Review)

Wallace, J., **Adler-Johnson, L.**, Jones, L., James, D., Davis, B. (October 2024). Stepping back: Building equity in academic collaborations and technical assistance. Oral presentation at the American Public Health Association Annual Meeting. Minneapolis, MN.

Adler-Johnson, L. (July 2024). Using R to Co-Create an Inclusive Data Analysis Approach with the HBCU Health Equity Data Consortium. Oral presentation at the useR! Annual Conference. Salzburg, Austria.

Johnson, L. C., Neuroth, L. M., Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., Harmon, K. J. (April 2023). Novel application of a data linkage framework NC-VDRS suicide deaths, 2019-2020. Poster presentation at the Society for Advancement of Violence and Injury Research Annual Conference. Denver, CO.

Neuroth, L. M., **Johnson, L. C.**, Fliss, M. D., Waller, A. E., Harmon, K. J. (April 2023). Applying a probabilistic data linkage approach to identify prior-year emergency department visits among violent death decedents in North Carolina, 2019-2020. Poster presentation at the Society for Advancement of Violence and Injury Research Annual Conference. Denver, CO.